Guide to the United Ministries in Higher Education Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
United Ministries in Higher Education Records
1942-2002
RG 104
Yale University Divinity School Library
26
(63 boxes)
Organizational and program materials of the UMHE and related bodies provide an overview of three decades of Protestant campus ministries. United Ministries in Higher Education was established in 1964, emerging out of the United Campus Christian Fellowship, a body that represented the student Christian movements of four Protestant denominations. By 1968 six more denominational agencies had joined the UMHE. In 1979 UMHE changed its name to United Ministries in Education, joining with Ministries in Public Education. In 1988 this partnership was ended and the UMHE was reorganized as The Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Higher Education (though still incorporated as United Ministries in Education).
United Ministries in Higher Education
Barker, Verlyn L.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of the UMHE, 1997, Verlyn L. Barker, 2006, and H. Lynn Jondahl, 2010
Biographical / Historical
United Ministries in Higher Education evolved out of several decades of ministry in non-church related institutions of higher education in the U.S. Organizationally, UMHE emerged out of the United Campus Christian Fellowship, which was a uniting in 1960 of the student Christian movements of the Evangelical United Brethren Church, the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), the United Church of Christ, and the United Presbyterian Church. These UCCF denominations formed UMHE in 1964 and by 1968 six more denominations had joined forces: the Moravian Church (1965), the Presbyterian Church, U.S. (1966), the Church of the Brethren (1967), the Episcopal Church (1968), the Reformed Church in America (1968), and the American Baptist Church (1968). The United Methodist Church became a member at its formation - the uniting of the Methodist Church with the Evangelical United Brethren church. In 1976, the Reformed Church in America restructured and withdrew from participation.
In 1966 the United Campus Christian Fellowship merged into the University Christian Movement in the United States, a body that was not integrally related to the institutional church in the same way that the UCCF had been. The UMHE continued to pursue its goal of developing strategy and recommending policy for ministries in higher education for the denominations it represented, striving to promote common initiatives rather than unilateral actions.
From 1964 to 1968 UMHE was governed by a Council for Policy and Strategy, a Committee of Administrators, and a Secretariat. In the fall of 1968, the National Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education was formed by the ten national denominational agencies that were supporting UMHE, a restructuring intended to place discussion and decision making in the hands of a more representative body of persons, to clarify staff accountability, and to improve the coordination of the campus ministries of the denominations. A Self-Study Committee was established in 1973 to oversee an extensive organizational analysis that led to the formation of a UMHE Policy Board in 1974.
The Policy Board of UMHE and the Program and Policy Committee of an organization called Ministries in Public Education created a Joint UMHE-MPE Committee in 1978 to investigate means for closer working and organizational relations between the two ministries. This Committee recommended the formation of United Ministries in Education as the successor to MPE and UHME. This change in the name and purpose of UMHE was consented to by the New York State Education Department on August 24, 1979.
The partnership between UMHE and MPE was dissolved in 1988 and The Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Higher Education was officially constituted on November 15, 1989 for a three-year period beginning January 1, 1990 (still operating under the corporate name of United Ministries in Education). UMHE was empowered to pursue an agenda in higher education ministries during this period of evaluation of both the program and the organization itself. Denominations supporting the Team included the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), the Episcopal Church, the United Church of Christ, the Presbyterian Church U.S.A., the Moravian Church, and the Church of the Brethren. The role of UMHE in relation to denominational activities and the new Higher Education Ministries Arena of the National Council of Churches was evaluated.
Scope and Contents
These records complement other holdings at the Yale Divinity Library, including RG 54: Archives of the New England Commission for United Ministries in Higher Education (1967-1974), RG 64: Archives of the National Campus Ministry Association, and RG 62: Records of the Danforth Study of Campus Ministries, as well as the archives of various student Christian movements. The constellation of these various record groups provides opportunity for study of the complex mix of ecumenical and denominational efforts at religious work on campuses in the U.S.
The Correspondence and Office Files of Series I and Organization and Policy Records of Series II are interrelated, with the chronological filing sequence of Series I running from 1962 to 1989 and Series II divided into four subsections: Annual Reports (1966-1985), Minutes (1964-1994), Legal and Policy Documents (1964-1992), and Personnel records (1962-1991). Records predating the formation of United Ministries in Higher Education relate to the body out of which it evolved.
Series III, Program Files and Reports, provides substantive documentation of the programs initiated and supported by UMHE, including the Health and Human Values project, Task Force on the Generational Process, and so forth. These program files are complemented by the Publications of Series IV, which address a wide range of issues related to ministry in higher education, and the State Commissions records of Series V. Financial records are available in Series VI for the years 1979 to 1986.
Material collected in Series VII documents various organizations related to the work of the UMHE, including the United Campus Christian Fellowship, out of which UMHE evolved.
Series VIII comprises records of the Christian Faith and Higher Education Institute, a program of UMHE. These materials were added in 2010 by H. Lynn Jondahl, who was Director of Resources and later Director of the Institute. The Christian Faith and Higher Education Institute operated from 1962 through 1971 with financial support from the American Baptist Church, the Protestant Episcopal Church, the United Church of Christ and the United Presbyterian Church. Several other denominations were involved in the program and policy of the Institute, including the Disciples of Christ, the Evangelical United Brethren and the Moravian Church in America, and the National Lutheran Council.
Series IX contains papers related to the church and higher education from the files of Verlyn L. Barker, who was Secretary, Ministries in Higher Education, United Church Board for Homeland Ministries and President of United Ministries in Higher Education. These materials, which supplement papers added earlier to Series IV, Publications, provide a valuable consolidated resource for studying the role and development of ecumenical Christian work at colleges and universities.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence and Office Files, 1962-1989
II. Organization and Policy Records, 1964-1994
III. Program Files and Reports, 1959-1993, n.d.
IV. Publications, 1955-1996
V. State Commissions, 1957-1993, n.d.
VI. Financial Records, 1979-1986
VII. Related Organizations and Material, 1944-1995, n.d.
VIII. Christian Faith and Higher Education Institute, 1962-1971
IX. Addendum: Verlyn Barker Files
Church work with students -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Clergy; United Ministries in Education; United Ministries in Higher Education
- Correspondence and Office Files, 1962-1989; Series I
  - Correspondence and Office Files, 1962-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
  - Correspondence and Office Files, 1979-1983 (Box 27, Folder 331-336)
  - Correspondence and Office Files, 1984-1988 (Box 28, Folder 337-341)
  - Correspondence and Office Files, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 365)
- Organization and Policy Records, 1964-1994; Series II
  - Annual reports
    - Annual Reports, 1966-67 (Box 36, Folder 401)
    - Annual Reports, 1973, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
    - Annual Report, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 402)
    - Annual Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 34, Folder 387-388)
  - Minutes
    - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1985-1994 (Box 36, Folder 403)
    - Minutes of Various Committees, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 135-153)
    - Minutes of Various Committees, 1968-1971 (Box 10, Folder 154-178)
    - Minutes of Various Committees, 1972-1977 (Box 11, Folder 179-198)
    - Minutes of Various Committees, 1978-1989 (Box 29, Folder 344-355)
    - Minutes of Various Committees, 1990-1994 (Box 30, Folder 356-360)
  - Legal and Policy Documents
    - Articles of Operation, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Proposed Corporate Name Change from UME back to UMHE, 1989 (Box 36, Folder 404)
    - Histories of the UMHE; Evaluation report of the Higher Education Ministries Team of UMHE, 1977- 1992 (Box 36, Folder 405)
    - Legal Documents (Box 36, Folder 406)
    - Policy Planning Committee, 1974-1983 (Box 36, Folder 407)
    - Policy Board, 1963-1973 (Box 5, Folder 82-95)
    - Policy Board, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 96-97)
    - Policy Board, 1976-1977 (Box 36, Folder 408-409)
    - Policy Board, 1978 (Box 35, Folder 398)
    - Policy Board, 1979 (Box 30, Folder 364)
    - Policy Board, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Policy Board, 1980-1981 (Box 32, Folder 375-376)
    - Policy Board, 1982-1983 (Box 33, Folder 377-378)
    - Policy Board, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 362)
    - UMHE Evaluation, 1968-1977 (Box 7, Folder 114-118)
  - Personnel Records
    - Office of Executive Secretary, 1971-1991 (Box 36, Folder 410)
    - Personnel, 1962-1970 (Box 4, Folder 69-78)
    - Personnel, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 79-80)
- Program Files and Reports, 1959-1993, n.d.; Series III
  - Bay Area Radical Education Project, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Black Higher Education, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19-23)
  - Career Development: Pamphlets, 1974-1986 (Box 37, Folder 411-412)
  - Career Development: Richard N. Bolles (Box 37, Folder 413)
  - Career Development: Correspondence between Richard Bolles and Verlyn Barker (Box 37, Folder 414)
  - Career Development: Documents (Box 37, Folder 415)
  - Career Development: Miscellaneous, 1974-1986 (Box 35, Folder 392)
  - Career Development: Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 416)
  - Church and Education, 1983-1984 (Box 38, Folder 417-418)
  - Community College Advisory Committee, 1974-1981 (Box 34, Folder 385)
  - Community College Programs, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 39-45)
  - Convocation, 1984 (Box 38, Folder 419)
  - Creationism, 1982 (Box 34, Folder 389)
  - Cross-Cultural Unity, 1979-1980 (Box 34, Folder 390)
  - Cultural Pluralism, 1976 (Box 38, Folder 420)
  - Ecumenical Relations, 1983-1988 (Box 38, Folder 421)
  - Emerging National Network, 1983 (Box 38, Folder 422)
  - Ethnic Higher Education, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Executives and Liaison Staff, 1979-1981 (Box 33, Folder 379-381)
  - Film Presentation, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Ford Foundation, info prepared for, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Foundation Donors and Prospects, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Haystack Meeting (Box 45, Folder 477)
  - Health and Human Values, Committee on (HHV), 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Health and Human Values: General Documents, 1962-1984 (Box 38, Folder 423-424)
  - HHV: Notes, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - HHV: Nursing Education, 1983-1984 (Box 38, Folder 425)
  - HHV: Primary Care Project, 1979-1983 (Box 38, Folder 426)
  - HHV: Yale Press Project, 1980-1983 (Box 38, Folder 427)
  - HHV: Society for Health and Human Values, 1983-1987 (Box 39, Folder 428)
  - Insitute for Social Policy Studies: Documents, 1972-1987 (Box 39, Folder 429)
  - ISPS: Office of Personnel Services, 1976-1981 (Box 39, Folder 430)
  - ISPS: Aesthetics and Theology, 1974-1987 (Box 39, Folder 431)
  - ISPS: Community Colleges, 1976-1981 (Box 39, Folder 432)
  - ISPS: Legal Education, 1975-1979 (Box 39, Folder 433)
  - Latin American Policy, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 50-56)
  - Legal Education Projects, 1978-1982 (Box 35, Folder 392b)
  - Liaison Staff, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 434)
  - Lilly Endowment, info prepared for, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 57-59)
  - Mass Communications, 1968, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 60-61)
  - Militarism and Education, 1978-1982 (Box 28, Folder 342)
  - Ministry in a Changing World, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 400)
  - Motive (merger offer), 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - National Commission, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Nationwide, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 65-68)
  - Partnership for Mission, 1979-1986 (Box 35, Folder 393)
  - Peace Education, 1979-1983 (Box 28, Folder 343)
  - Peacemaking, Militarism and Education, 1977-1993 (Box 41, Folder 441-442)
  - Plan of Ministry, 1973, 1978-1980 (Box 34, Folder 382)
  - Pluralism, 1977-1979 (Box 40, Folder 435)
  - Priority Program, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Program Report and Staff Evaluation, 1992 (Box 30, Folder 361)
  - Public Education, 1979-1983 (Box 31, Folder 373)
  - Science and Technology: Documents (ST), 1976-1986 (Box 40, Folder 436-437)
  - ST: Minutes of Exploratory Committee, 1983-1989 (Box 40, Folder 438)
  - ST: Moral Reasoning Project, 1985-1991 (Box 40, Folder 439)
  - ST: Consultation on Science, Technology and the Church, 1989 (Box 40, Folder 440)
  - Self-Study, 1968-1973 (Box 6, Folder 102-110)
  - Task Force on the Generational Process, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 111-113)
  - Task Force on Restructure, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 363)
  - Urban Mission Strategy, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 119)
- Publications, 1955-1996; Series IV
  - Programmatic
    - Advocacy Law Dictionary, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - Campus Ministry Bulletin, 1970-1971 (Box 41, Folder 443)
    - Common Thread, 1991-1995 (Box 43, Folder 468)
    - Directory, 1965-1996 (Box 41, Folder 444-446)
    - Directory: Ministry to Blacks in Higher Education, 1971-1973, 1981-1982, 1992 (Box 42, Folder 447)
    - Faith and Learning, 1995-1996 (Box 58, Folder 553)
    - Findings from the Ministries, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 121a-b)
    - Newsletters about Life/Works Planning, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Press Releases, 1969, 1975, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Probe, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1984 (Box 8, Folder 126-134)
    - Resources for Ministry in Higher Education, 1990s (Box 58, Folder 554)
    - UME Letter, 1980-1984 (Box 31, Folder 368)
    - UME Report, 1968-1969 (Box 43, Folder 469)
  - UMHE/UME articles and essays
    - Altbach, Philip. "Student Politics and Higher Education in the United States" (Box 43, Folder 448)
    - Barker, Verlyn. "The Role of the Minister in Higher Education", 1966 (Box 43, Folder 449)
    - Barker, Verlyn. "The Role of Mission", 1978 (Box 43, Folder 449)
    - Barker, Verlyn. "The Minister in Higher Education: Theologian, Mentor and Educator", 1989 (Box 43, Folder 449)
    - Barker, Verlyn and Van Hooris, Richard. "Index for Higher Education Programs and Resources" (Box 43, Folder 449)
    - Barnes, Ronald. "Where the Action Is", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 450)
    - Barnes, Ronald. "Some Problems Facing Higher Education" and "The Role of the Campus Ministry in Confronting Problems Facing Higher Education", 1965 (Box 43, Folder 450)
    - Bluford, Robert, Jr. "Toward Closing the Gap", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 451)
    - Demerath, N.J. "Campus Religion Student Values: Radical Rhetoric and Traditional Reality", 1969 (Box 43, Folder 452)
    - Elliot, Willis E. "Violence: No Resort or Last Resort or...?", 1967 (Box 43, Folder 453)
    - Findley, Cecil. "Evangelism and Stewardship on Campus" (Box 43, Folder 454)
    - Goodman, Paul. "Student Chaplains", 1967 (Box 43, Folder 455)
    - Green, Edith. "Tomorrow was Yesterday", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 456)
    - Gribbon, Robert. "Congregational Ministry in a Learning Society", 1980 (Box 31, Folder 370)
    - McAnulty, Henry. "The University: She Used to be Such a Lady", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 457)
    - McNeur, Linda. "The Artists as Recorders of History-in-the-Making" (Box 43, Folder 458)
    - Scheinfeld, Aaron. "Focus/Latin America", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 459)
    - Shinto, William Mamouro. "Colorful Minorities and the White Majority" (Box 43, Folder 463)
    - Smith, Harry. "Congregation and Higher Education", 1968 (Box 43, Folder 464)
    - Springer, J. "Handbook and Tool Kit for College and Religious Community Cooperation" (Box 43, Folder 465)
    - Statello, Daniel. "Nuts and Bolts: Planning for Ministry in Higher Education", 1976 (Box 43, Folder 466)
    - Murray, Andrew. "Peace and Conflict Studies as Applied Liberal Arts", 1980 (Box 31, Folder 372)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community College Paper 1: Ministry and the Community College by William E. Hallman, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 2: Community Development and the Church by Robert A. Mayo, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 3: Religion and the Community College by Roger Schmidt, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 4: Report of the Northwest Conference on the Community College and the Church, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 5: After the Boom...What now for the Community Colleges? by Edmund J. Gleazer, Jr., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 6: The Local Church and The Community College by Mary Alice Geier (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 7: A Case Method Approach to Developing A Ministry with Community Colleges by Earl J. Lowell (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 8: College as a Moral Community (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 9: Career Education and Elitism, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 10: Action-Research: A New Style of Politics, Education, and Ministry, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 11: A Plan for Mission (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 12: The Community Colleges: Opportunities for the Church to Create New Staffing Patterns for Ministry in Higher Education (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 13: Centering-Venturing: An approach to student development (Box 43, Folder 459)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 16: Meritocracy II by Dr. Dale Tillery (Box 43, Folder 460)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 17: A Design for Cross-Cultural Unity (Box 43, Folder 461)
    - Perspectives on Church and Community: Paper 18: The Church and the Community College: Partnership in Ministry by William H. Tiemann, 1981 (Box 43, Folder 461)
    - Public Education Policy Studies:"Education in a Global Age", 1980 (Box 31, Folder 368b)
    - Public Education Policy Studies: "Creationism, The Church, and the Public School", 1983 (Box 31, Folder 369)
    - Public Education Policy Studies: "Tuition Tax Credits", 1984 (Box 35, Folder 395)
    - Public Education Policy Studies: "How Should Christian Be Involved in the Public Area", n.d. (Box 35, Folder 396)
    - Reardon, Betty. "Militarization, Security and Peace Education: A study program for concerned Christians", 1981 (Box 31, Folder 371)
    - Van Voorlis, Richard. "Ministry in a Changing World", 1967 (Box 43, Folder 467)
    - Waters, Brent. "Science, Technology, and the Christian Faith", 1985 (Box 35, Folder 394)
  - Other articles and essays
    - Albright, Edwin, Jr. "A Plan for Mission", n.d. (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Aller, Susan B. "Plymouth House Ministry to Students", Advance, 1957 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Ames, David A. and Paradise, Scott. "Ministry in Higher Education: An Episcopal Church Perspective", 1984 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Anderson, David and Nash, John (eds) "Issue: those who make the waves", (Berkeley, CA: Publications Commission of the University Church Council)., 1965 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Association of American Colleges, "The Role of the Institutionally Appointed Campus Professional Religious Leadership", 1972 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Barnes, Ronald. "The Role of Campus Ministry in Confronting Problems Facing Higher Education", 1965 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Barnes, Ronald. "Some Problems Facing Higher Education", 1965 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Bluford, Robert. "The Church's Rationale for the Ministry in Higher Education", 1967 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Bluford, Robert. "What Constitutes an Effective Campus Ministry?", 1966 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Braun, Theodore. "United Student Fellowship Holds Final Assembly", United Church Herald, 1959 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Buerk, John A. "The Changing Role of the Protestant Campus Minister", 1965 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Buerk, John A. "The Theological Task of the Campus Ministry"., 1967 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Butzin, Peter. Untitled Talk, 1972 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Cantelon, John. "Our Current Understanding of the Ministry", 1960 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Center for the Study of Campus Ministry, Valparaiso University IN:"Ecumenical Relationships in Campus Ministry and Our Ministry with Others", 1974.; "The Mission of the Church in Higher Education: A Report of a Conference", 1976; "Yearbook IV", 1981; "Final Newsletter", Fall, 1987. (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Chapel and College, Spring 1963, published by National Association of College and University Chaplains and Director of Religious Life, with focus on the university chaplaincy as a profession. (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - "The Church and Higher Education", Proceedings of the 1967 Conference, University of North Dakota (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Clarke, Robert W. "Reflections on the Campus ministry in the Urban Setting"., 1964 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Click, Joanne. "How Can Churches Help Provide a Campus Ministry?", 1966 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Colwell, Ernest Cadman. "Blazing New Trails in Campus Religious Life", 1962 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Conn, Robert H. "Campus Ministry: A Mandate for Wholeness", Plumbline: A Journal of Ministry in Higher Education, 1984 (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Crockett, Larrimore. "The Urgency and Risk of the Campus Ministry: A sermon" (Box 43, Folder 470)
    - Davis, Kortright. "The Deepening of Higher Education", 1990 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Davison, James. "The Campus Minister: His Role and Responsibility" (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Department of Higher Education, National Council of Churches. "The Campus Ministry: A series of Reports on Ministries Across the Country", 1966 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Department of Campus Christian Life, Division of Local church Life and Work, Texan Association of Christian Churches. "Campus Christian Life in Texas", 1963 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Department of Campus Christian Life, Presbyterian Church U.S. "The Religious Student Center and the Campus Ministry", 1966 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Division of College and University Work, National Lutheran Council. "The Church and the University in Ferment", 1966 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Division of Presbytery Ministries, Committee on Higher Education, Grace Presbytery, "State of the Art in Higher Education", 1986 (Box 44, Folder 471)
    - Doerr, Lawrence. "The Ministry of the Laity and the Enabling Role of the Campus Minister", 1962 (Box 44, Folder 471)